Soviet Union Protestant Church Subject Files, Inclusive: 1886-1904, 1961-2019, undated, Bulk: 1990-1999.
Baylor University, The Keston Center for Religion, Politics, and Society
Soviet Union Protestant Church Subject Files
Inclusive: 1886-1904, 1961-2019, undated, Bulk: 1990-1999.
Baylor University, The Keston Center for Religion, Politics, and Society http://www.baylor.edu/kestoncenter/
55
Keston Institute, 1969 -
18 folders
The Soviet Union Protestant Church Subject Files contain documents primarily regarding missionary work and churches in the Siberia region. There are also references to existing religions in this area and to persecution.
Administrative Information
Physical Description
General condition: Good.
Biography/Profile
Keston College, originally founded in 1969 as the Center for the Study of Religion and Communism with the named changed to Keston College in 1974, collected and publicized details about religious persecution behind the Iron Curtain, becoming “the voice of the voiceless.” After the collapse of communism in the 1990s, Keston College moved to Oxford and downsized due to decreased funding. The name eventually changed to Keston Institute. In 2007, the Institute transferred the Keston Archive and Library to the newly created Keston Center for Religion, Politics, and Society at Baylor University.
Keston collected, verified, translated, and disseminated information received from believers in the Soviet Union, Poland, Romania, Czechoslovakia, Hungary, Yugoslavia, Bulgaria and other communist countries. The Keston Archive and Library housed numerous letters, petitions, reports and underground publications (Samizdat) from believers of various denominations along with officially published books and periodicals.
The Keston Center received various documents on Protestants within the Soviet Union from 1886 to 2019 with the majority of the content centered around the decade of the 1990s. The most common topics are missionary work and Protestant Churches in the Siberia region.
Immigrants spread Protestantism to Russian soon after the 1517 Reformation through the early 1700s, and around 1787. Expansion into Protestant lands in the early 1700s and 1800s allowed the incorporation of a wider Protestant population. Throughout these periods, the primary denominations represented appear to have been Lutheranism, Calvinism, and Mennonite. The early 1800s saw the influence of Pietism, and the latter half of the century witnessed the introduction of Baptist faith. The turn of the 20th century introduced Seventh-Day Adventist, Pentecostalism, and the Salvation Army by missionaries.
Scope and Content
The Soviet Union Protestant Church Subject Files contain correspondence, clippings, abstracts, newspapers, articles, book chapters, bibliographies, reports, a book review, a journal article, a magazine article, a pamphlet, and an issue of East-West Church Report. The most popular subjects within the files are missionary work and the Siberia region. Some additional topics referenced multiple times include Seventh-day Adventists, Pentecostals, Baptists, persecution, Jehovah’s Witnesses, atheist propaganda, and Shamanism. Also mentioned commonly as belief systems prevalent in various areas are Animism, Buddhism, and Islam.
Arrangement
The Keston Center received the Soviet Union Protestant Church documents in a singular file with an additional unmarked folder and Presbyterian specific folder. Each document has been organized by its subject designation and date. The Presbyterian file has remained in a separate folder and series within this collection.
The Soviet Union Protestant Church Subject Files are organized into two series: I. General and II. Presbyterians.
Access Restrictions
All requests for copying of materials must be submitted to the Keston Center for Religion, Politics, and Society in writing. Please use the Request Form for Copying Materials sheet. Unpublished materials authored or otherwise produced by the creator (s) of this collection are in the public domain. There are no restrictions on use. Copyright status for other collection materials is unknown. Transmission or reproduction of materials protected by U.S. Copyright Law (Title 17, U.S.C.) beyond that allowed by fair use requires the written permission of the copyright owners. Works not in the public domain cannot be commercially exploited without permission of the copyright owners. Responsibility for any use rests exclusively with the user.
Acquisition Information
Accession No. 55.
Related Resources
Related references
Shterin, Marat S., and Shterin. "Russia, Protestantism." In Religions of the World: A Comprehensive Encyclopedia of Beliefs and Practices, edited by J. Gordon Melton, and Martin Baumann. 2nd ed. ABC-CLIO, 2010. Accessed December 10, 2021.
Index Terms
Subjects (Organizations)
Keston College -- Archives.; Keston Institute -- Archives.
Places
Siberia (Russia) -- Religion.
Subjects
Baptists -- Soviet Union -- History.; Missionaries -- Soviet Union.; Pentecostals -- Soviet Union -- History -- 20th century.; Presbyterians -- Soviet Union.; Protestants -- Soviet Union -- History -- 20th century.; Seventh-Day Adventists -- Soviet Union.
Genres
Abstracts.; Articles.; Bibliographies.; Book reviews.; Clippings (Books, newspapers, etc.); Correspondence.; Newspapers.; Pamphlets.; Reports.
- General, 1886-1904, 1961-2019; 1
  Administrative Information
  Physical Description
  General condition: Good.
  Biography/Profile
  Correspondence, clippings, abstracts, newspapers, articles, book chapters, bibliographies, and an issue of East-West Church Report with details of missionary activity and churches in Russia, with a special focus on the Siberia region.
  Acquisition Information
  Accession No. 55.
  - Protestant Church. General, 1886-1904, 1961, 1967-1974, 1978, 1985, 1991 April, 2019, undated (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Protestant Church. History, 1988 January, 1992 January-September (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Protestant Church History. Soviet Period, 1986 March (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Individual Protestant Churches, 1993 November-1994 January, 1999 April (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Registration of Protestant Churches, 1998 December (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Oppressive practices relating to Protestant religious activity, 2005 May (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Oppressive practices against Protestants. Imprisonment (arrests: pre-trial detention; prison), undated (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Protestant Church Life, 1988-1999 March (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Protestant Church Life. Modernizations: attitudes and actions, 1980 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Protestant Church Life. Preaching; evangelism; conversions, 1990 February, 1998, 1999 July-August (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Protestant Church. Parish Life, 1998 June-July (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Protestant Church Life. Official Publications, 1997 December, 2000 April-October (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Protestant Church Life. Revival; Charismatic Renewal, 1979 June, undated (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Protestant Church Life. Philanthropy, 1996 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Protestant clergy, priesthood. Individuals. Friedrich, Hans-Peter, 1982 May (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Protestant Church. Public Demonstrations, Protests, 1999 March (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Protestant Church. Reactions with Fellow Believers, 2002 February (Box 1, Folder 17)
- Presbyterians, 1995-1997; 2
  Reports on Zion Presbyterian Church in Moscow Oblast.
  - Protestant Church. Presbyterians, 1995 May, 1997 July-November (Box 1, Folder 18)